Guide to the Records of the Bureau of Public Occasions RG.4.2
New York University Archives
Records of the Bureau of Public Occasions
1935-1976
1950-1976
New York University Archives
New York University. Bureau of Public Occasions
RG.4.2
16.73 Linear Feet in 34 boxes
The Records of the Bureau of Public Occasions contain a wide array of information related to the planning and hosting of University public events, commencement and commencement-related programs. The records are arranged alphabetically in one series and consist mainly of administrative records, correspondence, drafts, notes, telegraphs, photographs, and photo contact sheets.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical Note
The Bureau of Public Occasions was first created under Chancellor Elmer Ellsworth Brown in 1930, originally under the name of Bureau of Public Information. By 1933 Chancellor Harry Woodburn Chase changed the name to the Bureau of Public Occasions. Originally, the Bureau of Public Occasions reported to the Office of the Vice Chancellor and Secretary of the University and the role of Director of the Bureau of Public Occasions was part-time. However, as the demands for services grew and the Bureau was utilized by all schools and departments, on September 1, 1954, the Director of the Bureau of Public Occasions became a full-time position. The Director of the Bureau also became Assistant Secretary of the University under Chancellor Henry Townley Heald. Then in 1974, under President James McNaughton Hester, the Bureau of Public Occasions was organizationally transferred to the office of Planning and Development. The Bureau of Public Occasions continued until 1976 when the then-Director Arthur Rubin became Director of the Office of External Affairs, Commencement and Special Events. The Bureau of Public Occasions and the Office of External Affairs, Commencement and Special Events were the precursors for NYU's current Office of University Events, which is a division of University Relations and Public Affairs.
Throughout its history, the Bureau of Public Occasions was involved in the implementation of University functions to which the public was invited, such as commencement and commencement-related events, the James Stokes Lectureship on Politics, the Charles F. Deems Lecture Series, Founders Day Honors Convocations, the inauguration of President James M. Hester and dedications of numerous University buildings. The Bureau's main responsibilities were to supervise and to coordinate the planning and implementation of any event considered a public occasion, averaging more than 400 a year. The Bureau was also charged with the responsibility of creating promotional materials for those events. The Bureau of Public Occasions worked with various departments within the University, including the Office of Information Services, the Office for University Development, the Office of Publication and Printing, and the Office of Property Supervision.
The Bureau of Public Occasions was also involved in planning some of the public events relating to the Hall of Fame for Great Americans and New York University's expansion into Puerto Rico. Information on these two locales is scattered throughout various collections in this repository, and this collection offers a partial record of their activities. The Hall of Fame for Great Americans (the first hall of fame in America) was conceived by Chancellor Henry Mitchell MacCracken. It was opened in 1901 and was located on the University Heights Campus of NYU. The building, which housed the Hall of Fame, the Temple of Fame, was designed by Stanford White, and it was intended to be a temple of American wisdom and valor. The selection of twenty-nine political and literary figures ranging from George Washington to Washington Irving was chosen by a panel of one hundred individuals. The Hall of Fame still stands today as part of the Bronx Community College campus.
In 1949 New York University's School of Education first offered courses for graduate credit in Puerto Rico in cooperation with the University of Puerto Rico. By 1960 the program offered eighteen courses. However, since only one-third of the course work for these degrees could be taken in Puerto Rico, students had to come to New York City for an academic year or two summers. As a result of this requirement and expanding class sizes, NYU established a Residence Center in Puerto Rico in the summer of 1961. From 1949 to 1961, approximately 1,500 educators enrolled and more than four hundred masters' degrees were awarded, six students completed doctorates in NYU's School of Education. Then, in 1963, Dr. Parmer L. Ewing was named Director of the Puerto Rico Program. The first New York University commencement in Puerto Rico, which was planned by the Bureau of Public Occasions, was held on December 9, 1969. The Bureau was also involved in planning the next two commencements: December 5, 1970, and December 4, 1971. These Commencements were distinct from the Commencements in New York and had their own honorary degree recipients.
During the time span of this collection there were five Directors of the Bureau of Public Occasions. In order of their appointment, they were:
Alvin Clayton Busse was Professor of Speech and Dramatics at NYU for thirty years. He was a native of Slayton, Minnesota, and graduated with a B.A. from Macalester College in 1921. In 1924 Alvin Busse received his M.A. from NYU. Busse was first appointed as Instructor of Speech at NYU in 1921 and received his first Assistant Professorship in 1928. In 1934 he was promoted to Associate Professor and in 1950 to Professor. Busse was the Director of the Bureau of Public Information from 1930 to 1933 while he was also the first Director of the Bureau of Public Occasions. Alvin Busse continued to serve as the Director of the Bureau of the Public Occasions until 1942, when he left on military leave; he then resumed his role as Director from 1945 to 1950. Busse served in the USMC during WWI and WWII.
Ormond J. Drake received his B.A. and M.A. from the University of Michigan in 1930 and 1931 respectively. He joined the faculty of NYU's College of Arts and Science as Professor of Speech and Chairman of the Department of Speech and Dramatics at NYU in September 1938, and in 1949 he was named Assistant Dean and Director of Admissions at College of Arts and Science. Drake was the Acting Director of the Bureau of Public Occasions from 1943 to 1945 and Director of the Bureau of Public Occasions from 1952 to 1956. Ormond Drake then went on to become the Associate Dean of the School of Continuing Education, and in 1956 Director of Town Hall. On March 10, 1965, Ormond J. Drake received a citation from Mayor Robert Wagner for distinguished and exceptional service.
Fred Crossland graduated from Brooklyn College in 1943 and received his M.A. in 1947 and Ph.D. in 1953, both from NYU. Crossland became a faculty member in NYU's School of Commerce, Accounts and Finance in 1947 and was promoted from Assistant Professor to Associate Professor of Political Science. From 1956 to 1959 Fred Crossland served as Assistant Secretary of the University and as Director of its Bureau of Public Occasions. In 1959 Crossland was named Director of Admissions and in 1962 was named Dean of Admissions. In 1964 Crossland left NYU to become a Program Associate in the Education Program of the Ford Foundation.
Morton C. Kimball served as the Director of the Bureau of Public Occasions from February 1, 1959, to August 31,1963, when he then became the Director of Housing at NYU.
Arthur H. Rubin received his B.S. from NYU's Business Education Department in the School of Education in 1951. In 1959 he received his M.A. in Guidance and Personnel Administration from NYU's School of Education. Rubin started his career at NYU in 1947 as an Administrative Assistant to the Assistant Dean of the School of Education. He was promoted to several positions before September 1963, when he was appointed Director of the Bureau of Public Occasions, succeeding Morton C. Kimball. On June 30, 1971, Rubin was awarded a presidential citation for "consistently high quality of the manner in which he has presented our institution to the public." In 1974 Rubin was promoted to Assistant VP for Public Occasions, a newly created position. In this same year, the Office of the Bureau of Public Occasions began to report to W.F. Payne, Executive Vice President for Planning and Development. In 1976 Rubin became Director of Extramural Affairs and later that year was named Associate Dean for Administration at the NYU College of Dentistry. In 1980 Rubin became Director of Alumni Affairs at NYU.
Source:
Frusciano, Thomas J. and Marilyn H. Pettit, New York University and the City: an illustrated history, 1831-1996. New Brunswick, NY: Rutgers University Press, 2007
Scope and Content Note
Materials in this collection date from June 11, 1935, to September 30, 1976, and a large portion of them pertain to commencement activities, especially the All-University Commencements held at University Heights from June 15, 1955, to June 10, 1964, and at Madison Square Garden from June 11, 1969, to June 5, 1975. Also included are the Commencements held in Puerto Rico in 1969, 1970 and 1971. Other events covered by the Bureau of Public Occasions include alumni events, freshman convocations, Gallatin Associates Dinners, the inauguration of Provost Norton Nelson in 1966, Presidential Honors (University Medals), including one awarded to Mrs. John F. Kennedy in 1962, building dedications and inductions into the Hall of Fame for Great Americans.
This collection consists of administrative files and as such contain typed and hand written correspondence and working notes and drafts. In the Commencement folders, materials consist of instruction manuals for the participants, commencement programs, admission tickets, contact photo sheets and original University Citations. In addition, the folders on the first Puerto Rico commencement include a number of black and white photographs. The folders on luncheons and dinners contain mailing lists for invitations, invitations and response cards, guest lists, seating charts, menus and catering invoices. For other University events, materials in this collection range from speeches with corresponding notes and drafts, press releases, newspaper and magazine articles, biographies, and throughout many of the files there are numerous Western Union Telegraphs.
Some documents, mostly correspondence, in the folders relating to NYU in Puerto Rico are in Spanish.
This collection also contains photographs of special events, some of which were held in Puerto Rico.
Related Material at the New York University Archives
Administration
Guide to the Office of the Chancellor and Executive Vice President 1952-1966 RG 6.0
Guide to the Administrative Papers of Chancellor/Executive Vice President Sidney Borowitz 1967-1977 RG 6.0.7
Gallatin Award Dinners, 1957-1985
Puerto Rico
Guide to the Administrative Files of the Dean of the School of Education, Daniel E. Griffiths 1948-1985 (Bulk 1965-1983) RG 26.0.1
Commencement/Special Events
Guide to the Office of Vice President for University Relations Records 1957-1962 RG 7.2.1
Guide to the Records of the Office of External Affairs, Commencement and Special Events 1975-1995 RG 7.4
Hall of Fame
Guide to the Administrative Papers of Chancellor Elmer Ellsworth Brown 1900-1937 RG 3.0.4
Guide to the Records of the Office of the University Architect/Joseph J. Roberto Collection 1928-1987 RG 11.4
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically and then chronologically in a single series.
Use Restriction
Permission to publish materials must be obtained in writing from the: New York University Archives, Elmer Holmes Bobst Library, 70 Washington Square South, New York, NY 10012, Phone: (212) 998-2646, Fax: (212) 995-4070, E-mail: university-archives@nyu.edu
Immediate Source of Acquisition
In May 2024, two folders containing photographs were transferred from the New York University Archives Photograph Collection (PHOTO 00001). The accession number associated with this accretion is 2024.029.
Clippings (information artifacts); Commencement ceremonies; Convocations; Instructions; Attendance lists; Photographs.; Pamphlets.; Programs (documents); Press releases.; Correspondence.; Notes.; Invitations.; Puerto Rico.; Awards; Administrative records; Award dinners; Lectures.; Private universities and colleges -- Administration -- United States.; New York (N.Y.).; Telegrams; Speeches.; New York University; New York University. Alumni Association; Gallatin Associates; Drake, Ormond J.; Kimball, Morton C.; Crossland, Fred; Deems, Charles F.; Busse, Alvin C.; New York University. School of Education; Elmer Holmes Bobst Library; Rubin, Arthur H; Onassis, Jacqueline Kennedy, 1929-1994; Nelson, Norton; Phelps, Anson G.; Voorhis, Howard O.; White, Stanford, 1853-1906; New York University. Hall of Fame for Great Americans; Chase, Harry Woodburn, 1883-1955; Heald, Henry T. (Henry Townley), 1904-1975; New York University. University Heights; Hester, James M., 1924-2014; MacCracken, Henry Mitchell, 1840-1918; Newsom, Carroll V. (Carroll Vincent), 1904-1990; Kimball, LeRoy Ellwood, 1888-; Stokes, James; New York University -- Buildings; New York University. School of Engineering and Science; New York University -- Administration -- 20th century; New York University -- Presidents; New York University -- History -- 20th century
- Series I: General Files, 1935-1976; 1950-1975; 33 boxes
  - African Resources, Conference on, 1961 March 28 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Agnon, Dr. S. Y. (Israel). Presentation of Neuman Literary Prize to, 1963 July 17 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Altschul House, Dedication of, 1960 November 21 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Alumni Association of Puerto Rico, 22nd Annual Assembly, 1971 December 4 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Alumni Club of Chicago, Meeting, 1965 May 27 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Alumni Club of New Jersey, Dinner, 1963 March 22 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Alumni Club of Washington, D.C., Dinner, 1963 October 3 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Alumni Dinner, 1963 March 26 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Alumni Dinner, 1963 April 23 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Alumni Dinner, 1963 May 14 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Alumni and Faculty, Champagne Dance, 1974 May 10 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Alumni Federation, Annual Conference, 1964 January 31 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Alumni Federation, Board of Directors, Reception, 1964 June 3 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Alumni Federation, Board of Directors, Reception, 1965 June 11 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Alumni Federation and New York University Club, Address to, 1962 January 4 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Alumni Fund Solicitors, speech to, 1962 October 30 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - American Association of University Professors, Address to, by President James M. Hester, 1962 March 8 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Arthur, James, Lecture Series, 1969 February 18 and March 4 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Arthur, James, Lecture Series, 1975 April 16-17 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Association of American Universities and visiting Vice-Chancellors of the Association of Universities of the British Commonwealth, Joint Reception, 1962 April 5 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Baccalaureate Service, 1952 June 8 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Baccalaureate Service, 1971 June 6 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Baccalaureate Service, University Heights, 1970 June 7 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Baccalaureate Service, Washington Square, 1970 June 7 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Backman, Grace and Jules, Amphitheatre, Dedication of, 1972 October 12 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Backman, Jules, Presidential Citation to, 1964 October 7 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Baer, Dean William Bush, Presidential Tribute to, 1958 January 26 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Balewa, Alhaji Sir Abubakar Tafawa, Honorary Degree (LLD) awarded to, 1961 July 31 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Begrisch, Frank, Hall, Dedication of, 1961 June 3 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bellevue Medical Center, Cornerstone Ceremony, 1952 November 7 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Berol, Alfred C., Collection of the works of Lewis Carroll, Reception in honor of the acquisition, 1975 March 12 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Betancourt, Romulo, President of Venezuela, University Medal awarded to, 1963 February 21 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Biruni-Rumi International Conference, 1974 January 28-29 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Board of Trustees Dinner, 1970 June 8 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Board of Trustees Dinner, 1971 June 6 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Board of Trustees Dinner, 1972 May 30 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Bobst, Elmer Holmes, Library, Dedication of: Correspondence (1972 October 3 - 1973 January 29), 1972 December 16 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Bobst, Elmer Holmes, Library, Dedication of: Ceremony, 1972 December 16 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Bobst, Elmer Holmes, Library, Dedication of: Photographs, 1972 December 16 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Bobst, Elmer Holmes, Library, Dedication of: Printed Materials, 1972 December 16 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Bobst, Elmer Holmes, Library, Dedication of: Publicity, 1972 December 16 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Bobst, Elmer Holmes, Library, Dedication Dinner, 1972 December 16 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Bobst, Elmer Holmes, Library, Open House: Folder #1, 1973 October 12 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Bobst, Elmer Holmes, Library, Open House: Folder #2, 1973 October 12 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Bobst, Elmer Holmes, Library, Pre-Dedication Luncheon, 1971 May 20 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Bobst, Elmer Holmes, 90th Birthday Celebration, 1974 December 15 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Bohr, Dr. Niels, Lecture, 1957 December 2 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Brazil, Conference on, 1958 December 1-3 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Brazilian Institute, Conference on, 1962 January 11 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Briand, Aristide, 80th Birthday Commemoration, 1942 March 28 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - British Commonwealth, Association of Universities of, 1958 Septermber 17-19 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Brotherhood Week Program at NYU, 1959 February 18 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Burnet, Sir Macfarlane, University Medal awarded to, 1962 April 2 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Business Administration, Graduate School of, Alumni Association, Annual Dinner, 1961 June 5 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Business Administration, Graduate School of, Alumni Association, Annual Dinner, 1962 June 4 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Business Administration, Graduate School of, Foreign Students Orientation Program, 1962 September 13 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Business Administration, Graduate School of, Groundbreaking, 1957 September 30 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Business Administration, Graduate School of, Pre-Commencement Ceremony, 1962 June 4 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Business Administration, Graduate School of, Pre-Commencement Ceremony, 1964 June8 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Business Administration, Graduate School of, Pre-Commencement Ceremony, 1975 June 4 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Cecil, Lord David, Lecture, 1975 April 23 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Charitable Foundations, Conference on, 1963 May 20 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Christian Foundation Convocation, 1960 May 9 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Clark, Lord Kenneth, "Civilization," film series, 1969 October 28- December 9 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Clark, Lord Kenneth, University Medal awarded to, 1964 April 14 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Clergy of Greenwich Village, Luncheon for, 1955 February 9 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Cochrane, Eddie Mae, Room (East Building), Dedication of, 1975 October 4 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Comedie Francaise, Luncheon, 1955 November 15 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Commencement Dinner, 1935 June 11 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Commencement Dinner, 1936 June 9 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Commencement Dinner, 1937 June 8 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Commencement Dinner, 1938 June 7 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Commencement Dinner, 1939 June 6 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Commencement Dinner, 1940 June4 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Commencement Dinner, 1941 June 10 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Commencement Dinner, 1945 June 12 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Commencement Dinner, 1946 June 11 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Commencement Dinner, 1947 June 10 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Commencement Dinner, 1948 June 8 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Commencement Dinner, 1949 June 14 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Commencement Dinner, 1950 June 13 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Commencement Dinner, 1951 June 5 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Commencement Dinner, 1952 June 10 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Commencement Dinner, 1953 June 9 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Commencement Dinner, 1954 June 8 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Commencement Dinner, 1955 June 14 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Commencement Dinner, 1956 June 5 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Commencement Dinner, 1957 June 5 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Commencement Dinner, 1958 June 3 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Commencement Dinner, 1959 June 9 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Commencement Dinner, 1960 June 7 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Commencement Dinner, 1961 June 6 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Commencement Dinner, 1962 June 5 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Commencement Dinner, 1963 June 4 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Commencement Exercises: Folder 1, 1955 June 15 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Commencement Exercises: Folder 2, 1955 June 15 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Commencement Exercises, 1956 June 6 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Commencement Exercises, 1957 June 6 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Commencement Exercises, 1958 June 4 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Commencement Exercises, 1959 June 10 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Commencement Exercises, 1960 June 8 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Commencement Exercises, 1961 June 7 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Commencement Exercises, 1962 June 6 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Commencement Exercises, 1963 June 5 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Commencement Exercises, 1964 June 10 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Commencement Exercises, 1969 June 11 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Commencement Exercises: Correspondence (1970 May 2 - 1970 July 17), 1970 June 9 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Commencement Exercises: Other Material, 1970 June 9 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Commencement Exercises: Printed material-folder #1, 1970 June 9 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Commencement Exercises: Printed material-Folder #2, 1970 June 9 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Commencement Exercises: Publicity, 1970 June 9 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Commencement Exercises: Correspondence (1970 December 12 - 1971 July 15), 1971 June 7 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Commencement Exercises: Other Material, 1971 June 7 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Commencement Exercises: Printed Materials, 1971 June 7 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Commencement Exercises: Publicity, 1971 June 7 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Commencement Exercises: Correspondence (1971 October 1 - 1972 June 23), 1972 May 31 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Commencement Exercises: Other Material, 1972 May 31 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Commencement Exercises: Printed material-Folder #1, 1972 May 31 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Commencement Exercises: Printed material-Folder #2, 1972 May 31 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Commencement Exercises: Publicity, 1972 May 31 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Commencement Exercises: Other Material, 1973 June 5 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Commencement Exercises: Photographs, 1973 June 5 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Commencement Exercises: Printed materials-Folder #1, 1973 June 5 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Commencement Exercises: Printed materials-Folder #2, 1973 June 5 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Commencement Exercises: Other Material, 1974 June 6 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Commencement Exercises: Photographs, 1974 June 6 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Commencement Exercises: Printed materials-Folder #1, 1974 June 6 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Commencement Exercises: Printed materials-Folder #2, 1974 June 6 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Commencement Exercises: Correspondence (1975 February 6 - 1975 May 30), 1975 June 5 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Commencement Exercises: Other Material, 1975 June 5 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Commencement Exercises: Printed materials-Folder #1, 1975 June 5 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Commencement Exercises: Printed materials-Folder #2, 1975 June 5 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Commencement Exercises: Publicity, 1975 June 5 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Commencement Luncheon, 1945 June 13 (Box 10, Folder 9)